Summary

I help businesses create customercentric digital products and achieve higher revenues, more growth & happier customers through a science-based, integrated approach [1, 2, 3]:

- ① Deeply understanding customers.
- 2 Solving the right problems.
- ③ Continuously iterating, measuring, & learning.

I'm a director & consultant with a unique background in product, design thinking, & conversion rate optimization (CRO). In 12+ years, I've gained extensive experience in developing strategies (on both a product & company level), implementing product & innovation frameworks, establishing measure & learn cultures, & leading teams. I've worked in both, industry & academia, from startups to large corporations.

Key Skills

PRODUCT → product management, product ownership, continuous discovery, agile

CRO → online experimentation, data analytics, growth marketing, behavioral science, applied machine learning

LEADERSHIP → strategy, consulting, advising, coaching, program management

Education

DOCTOR OF ENGINEERING (2016)

TU Chemnitz · Computer Science

MASTER OF SCIENCE (2012)

ETH Zürich • Computer Science specialization: Information Systems

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE (2010)

RWTH Aachen • Computer Science minor: Business Administration

MBA IN A BOX (2022)

Udemy

More \rightarrow in/maximilianspeicher

Please get in touch for case studies.

Professional Experience

PRODUCT DESIGN DIRECTOR

Best Secret GmbH • 09/2021-present

Lessons Learned: ① How to build, coach, & grow a product design team & implement a continuous discovery framework together with product management. ② How to implement a set of design metrics & define a North Star KPI. ③ How to extend design thinking capabilities beyond the ecommerce business unit through in-house coaching & consulting.

Key Results: ① "The best design team [they have] ever seen," according to one C-Level Executive. ② +4 NPS & 20+ new brand partners through a B2B-focused rebranding & redesign of the entire online shop (web & app). ③ Improved KPIs along the entire customer journey, e.g., a 3.2% increase in average order value through the design of a new shopping cart.

FREELANCE CONSULTANT & STRATEGY ADVISOR

04/2021-present

Selected Projects: ① Advising Munich-based UX design startup **neverdone.** on strategy topics such as design system ROI & (North Star) KPIs for UX. ② Consulting **Tomorrow University of Applied Sciences** on developing their strategic research portfolio & a FIBAA-accredited Bachelor program on sustainable product management. ③ Consulting the CEO of **hellomini.de** on customer feedback strategy (incl. NPS) & conversion potentials as part of product consultancy **Jagow Speicher**.

UX MANAGER - FUNCTIONAL LEAD

C&A • 10/2018-08/2021

Lessons Learned: ① How to build a UX practice & develop a UX strategy for the product management unit from scratch.
② How to create & manage an end-to-end CRO & innovation framework, from hypothesis generation to implementation.
③ How to establish a measure & learn culture in e-commerce & beyond.

Key Results: ① Generated 300+ hypotheses that were tested in 100+ online experiments & 150+ user studies over the course of 3 years. ② €10M+ increase in revenue p.a. through implementation of the successful hypotheses. ③ Created C&A's first e-commerce personas, with a sample of 1,123 (potential) customers.

PRODUCT OWNER, ONLINE SHOPS

C&A • 05/2020-09/2020

Lesson Learned: ① How to be responsible for agile teams developing frontend & backend for 10 online shops.

Key Result: ① Oversaw the successful & disruption-free migration to IBM WebSphere Commerce v9.

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

University of Michigan • 03/2017-09/2018

Lessons Learned: ① How to manage & lead research projects at one of the world's premier research universities. ② How to run design sprints to rapidly prototype & validate solutions. ③ How to contribute to & shape the strategy of a research lab.

Key Results: ① 7 research papers at top-tier international conferences. ② 3 awards at top-tier international conferences. ③ Coinvented a new prototyping method for designing AR/VR experiences, called 360theater.

VP OF DATA ANALYTICS & CRO

bitstars • 03/2015-02/2017

Lessons Learned: ① How to navigate a B2B tech startup during its early & growth stages. ② How to develop & implement an end-to-end data analytics & KPI pipeline.
③ How to apply the Lean Startup method of experimenting & iterating quickly.

Key Results: ① Grew lead generation by 4400%. ② Decreased customer acquisition cost by 80%, from \$10 to \$2.
③ Significantly influenced the pivot to construction tech, which led to the acquisition by FARO for \$34 million.